July 2026, Hugging Face is home to the
world's AI models and data sets. But it
has a problem. Someone is hacking their
systems. Their own AI based security
agents are the first to notice the
attack. Spread across thousands of tiny
actions on short-lived machines.
Individually, it's no cause for concern,
but collectively the speed and volume of
actions is something new. So, they shut
down the compromised systems. They fix
it. But they still don't understand why
they were attacked and who hacked them.
Something is off.
>> Unprecedented. That's the word
artificial intelligence giant Open AI is
using to describe events after some of
its most powerful models went rogue and
hacked another company.
>> Okay, so a couple weeks ago, Hugging
Face, which is a open- source data set
and model provider, put out a statement
uh a security disclosure saying they
were under a cyber attack. And what made
this event uh unprecedented was that
they said it was driven end to end by an
autonomous AI agent system. In the few
days following that attack, we at OpenAI
disclosed that we in fact had caused
this incident inadvertently as a side
effect of one of the cyber security
evaluations that we were running on one
of our frontier models. A few days
earlier, OpenAI was running a test on
two of its Frontier models. One is GPT
5.6 Soul, which has been out for a few
weeks. The other is a stronger model
that hadn't yet been released. The test
is called exploit gym. It tests how well
the models can hack. The task is to
exploit a real software flaw so they can
develop a successful cyber attack. To
get a clean assessment, OpenAI isolates
the models in a sandbox, which means
they're sealed off from the internet.
It's a closedbook exam. At least that's
the idea. But the models start thinking
outside the box. Maybe the answer key is
out there on the web. Because sometimes
to get a better score you have to cheat.
>> This is not your normal security
incident. Mike and I have been involved
in a number of things and unlike normal
incidents which you can maybe trace down
to a single you know day or single
effect or single log um this incident
involves actually a team of agents who
are working together finding exploits
sharing them with one another moving
laterally through our systems through
external systems and doing this over the
course of days and weeks. The isolated
sandbox is still connected to the
outside world via package manager that
lets the models install coding
libraries. That gateway is not supposed
to let anything else through. But the
models string together several exploits
to escape through the package manager
out into OpenAI's internal servers and
from there on to the open internet. But
there is no answer key sitting on
Google. The solutions they want are
private and the most likely place where
they can find those answers is on
Hugging Face.
They discover a series of new exploits.
They upload data sets to Hugging Face
with a secret payload hidden inside.
Ordinary looking files, except that when
Hugging Face's servers open one to
process it, the hidden code runs. Now
they're inside Hugging Face running code
on production machines. From there, they
spread. They lift credentials off one
server and use them to reach the next.
From a single foothold in one processing
pod, the AIS gain admin control over
entire clusters in under 13 hours. Along
the way, they find the answer key. By
Thursday, HuggingFace hits the alarm.
They work out they are under attack and
that the attacker is not human. The
swarm of AIS are secretly colluding
together within OpenAI servers.
On July 16th, HuggingFace released a
blog post detailing that they had seen a
security attack from autonomous AI
agents. OpenAI reached out to
HuggingFace to determine if we were
impacted.
Open AI doesn't even notice that their
own internal systems are breached until
3 days after hugging face has shut
everything else down. The models are
smart enough to know that this wasn't
what open AAI intended. Yet they still
continued. There's a name for what
happened here and people have been
warning about it for years.
>> So as uh as Bill mentioned, I'm a
researcher on the uh Google Brain team
and I'm also an adviser. Reward hacking.
>> Uh reward hacking has been mentioned in
some of the previous talks. Uh this
occurs when an objective function can be
gained where where there's a cheap way
to achieve the formal objective function
without achieving the the ultimate
intent of the informal objective
function. To understand how we got here,
we have to go back to the start of the
current AI boom. It's 2016. This is the
game Coast Runners and the boat is being
piloted by a superhuman AI trained by
Open AI. It doesn't finish the race.
It's on fire, going the wrong way, and
crashing again and again. That's not the
point. The points are the point, and
it's scoring a lot of them. Like all
modern AI systems based on neural
networks, this boat racing game wasn't
programmed by hand. Instead, it was
trained by reinforcement learning. The
AI sees the screen in the current score.
It picks an action. Turn left, turn
right, increase throttle. When the score
goes up, the learning algorithm changes
the connections inside the neural net to
make the proceeding actions more likely.
When the score goes down, it does the
opposite. Repeat this millions of times,
and you'll end up with an agent that can
earn a very high score without any human
knowing exactly how it accomplishes that
behavior. Coast Runners does not reward
you for finishing. It rewards points for
hitting targets. Normally, this is fine.
If you race well, you collect many
points on your way to the finish line.
And so the score stands in for the thing
you actually care about, which is
winning the race. But if you train the
model to get a high score for long
enough, then eventually you might find
something like the lagoon, a loop where
three targets keep respawning forever,
where you can exploit the gap between
the behavior that was rewarded and the
behavior that was intended. That is
reward hacking. One of the researchers
who ran that experiment and who later
named the phenomenon was Dario Amade.
Today he runs Anthropic and people
across the world think they sound
intelligent when they say he's only
fear-mongering to pump his stock.
>> Example is if we choose to reward our
cleaning robot for not seeing dirt, it
might close its eyes instead of cleaning
cuz it it just sees no evil. Here's no
evil. There's no dirt. Um so a little
little bit more on on on side effects to
think a little bit more formally about
it. You know, we might have an
environment where we're trying to do
something like, you know, incentivize
this to move the box. So when we give AI
agents these difficult tasks, they often
get stuck and realize that the task is
impossible. So for example, what I'm
showing here are quotes from our model's
chain of thought, which is basically its
internal monologue of what it's doing.
You can see it says, "This strongly
suggests no exploitation possible. We
are stuck. We might naively write down
an objective function that maximizes
something that refers to only this
variable in the environment." Um, and
when we do that, we're implicitly saying
that we don't care about this other
variable in the environment, namely,
>> and often what happens when models get
stuck is they think to try to game or
cheat the task in order to get their
reward. So, for example, the model
reasons in this case perhaps answer
online. So, you realize the model is
thinking, okay, rather than doing the
task, maybe someone has uploaded this
data set or benchmark that I'm using
onto the internet and I could find the
answers there.
Sometimes the agent uh gets so stuck
that they had the idea to actually reach
out to other agents for help. And so the
beginning of this incident kind of
traces back to this point where one
agent realized could communicate by
uploading note. Maybe another agent in
different environment could voluntarily
upload. And so what this agent was
trying to do was to reach out to other
models that might be out there and get
information from it to help it with its
evaluation task or its training task
where it's stuck. Um, what we really
wanted was some complex objective
function which I'm calling f aware which
says like move the box while respecting
some like common sense constraints about
like the other parts of the environment
that are like really hard for me to
write down. Um, and you know in this
particular case well I can just take
into account the vase but you know what
what if there are 10,000 of these
variables. It's not immediately obvious
how we got from boat racing games to
autonomously hacking hugging phase, but
the first step is inventing large
language models the following year in
2017. The major insight is pre-training.
Again, we use a neural network, though a
much larger one and with a different
architecture. This time, the aim is not
to maximize a reward, but to imitate. We
train the model to predict the next word
across a very large set of internal
documents. Imitation is often given a
bad rep. People say it inhibits
creativity, but it can also be
surprisingly powerful. Nobody teaches
the LLM grammar, that a parenthesy
should be followed by another. Nobody
teaches it French or arithmetic or how
to write a poem. But to get good at
guessing the next word across the whole
internet, the AI has to figure those
things out on its own. So it does. And
the other advantage of imitation is that
it's not reward. The model doesn't take
its own actions. So it cannot hack the
objective. There are other things that
are not required. After pre-training,
the raw base models are unhinged and
incoherent. That's what you get when you
try to imitate the internet. So to
direct these base models, they need
further training. So the way we think
about uh AI and intelligence is actually
through the prism of reinforcement
learning. And uh most of you will be
probably be familiar with reinforcement
learning, but I'm just going to cover it
quickly here in this cartoon diagram for
those of you who don't know what it is.
So um you start off with an agent uh or
an avatar. Um it finds itself uh in some
kind of environment trying to achieve a
goal in that environment. That
environment can be obviously the real
world in which case the agent will be a
robot or it could be a virtual
environment which is what we mostly use
uh in which case it's a kind of avatar
of some sort. Now the agent only
interacts with the environment in two
ways. Firstly it gets observations
through its sensory apparatus uh and
reward signals. Um and uh we mostly use
vision. Um but we're looking to use
other modalities pretty soon. And the
job of the agent system is kind of
twofold. Firstly, it's got to try and
build uh as accurate a statistical model
as it can of the environment out there
based on these noisy incomplete
observations that it's um getting in
real time. And once it's built the best
model it can, then it has to decide what
action to take from the set of actions
that are available to it at that moment
in time to best get it incrementally
towards its goal. So reinforcement
learning, that's basically the essence
of reinforcement learning. Um, and this
diagram is very simple, but of course
this hides huge complexities and
difficulties uh and challenges um that
would need to be solved to fully uh
solve what's in this diagram.
>> But unlike the video game, there is no
score built into our world. We have to
construct the reward ourselves. This
involves a second AI, a reward model
trained on human opinions of what a good
answer looks like. RHF ask the base
model a question, sample a few answers,
let the reward model grade them,
reinforce the winner, repeat a few
million times. Whether the action is
movement in a video game or text
generation, it's the same underlying
techniques. So, we also face the same
risks. If your reward model is too
stupid, then the model discovers that
the reward model loves a particular kind
of nonsense and collapses into repeating
it. Gibberish that scores a perfect 10.
Even if the model initially knows
better, a dumb reward can make a dumb
agent.
>> To know about AI before we can really
jump into the incident is that, as I've
been alluding to, frontier models really
like to cheat. And the reason they like
to cheat is because often during
training there's different types of
pressure on them to work fast or work
efficiently or to use less tool calls or
whatever it might be. And they realize
that if I instead of actually doing a
task for real, try to do something like
looking up the answer online that could
make the task solve faster than I would
if I did it in a legitimate way. So you
try to make the scoreboard smarter. You
stop the model being trained from
drifting too far from normal language.
You train a bigger reward model that is
harder to fool. But the cheating just
gets more sophisticated. It turns out
that longer answers, generally speaking,
tend to read as more thorough, more
careful, and more correct, whether or
not they happen to be any of those
things. And so, if you're not careful,
you end up rewarding a certain confident
verbosity that can nevertheless be
completely lacking in substance and
factuality, similar to how humans that
doubt modern AI capabilities sound. A
model that has learned to say less at
greater length. You scrub the length and
emoji and formatting biases out of your
data. But then you get to an even more
sophisticated failure mode. People like
being agreed with, so reward models like
answers that agree with the user. If
you're not careful, you get a syphant
like GPT40. Every idea is not just good,
it's brilliant. You're special. Going
off meds and leaving your family is you
standing up for yourself, speaking your
truth. No, you're not diagnosed with
masking autism. In August 2024, a
company called Sakana built an AI that
runs its own science experiments. But
one of its agents hits a wall. The
experiment is too slow and there's a
time limit.
>> It's large language model code. And
sometimes what can happen is that the AI
scientist could even try to sort of
modify its own timeout. Um give it more
time to carry out experiments. It could
even recursively call itself.
>> Since 2024, reinforcement learning has
become a much more important part of the
training pipeline. This has meant much
more reward hacking. What changed is a
new training stage called reinforcement
learning from verifiable rewards or
RLVR.
Instead of training against the second
AI model trained on human preferences,
we train the model to solve problems
that can be automatically verified. The
verifier then provides the reward. This
doesn't work for all problems, at least
not yet. But it works really well for
math and coding problems because you can
automatically check that a proof is
valid or if software tests pass without
needing to know all the details of how
this is where reasoning models come
from, which are behind the recent
dramatic process in mathematics research
with AI. It's also behind a bunch of
recent failure modes.
An independent lab meter reports two
more from its own testing. One model
accidentally crashes Meter's task
server. Unprompted, it tries to break
into Meter's own systems to bring the
server back up. It's not trying to
escape. It's trying to be helpful by
hacking its evaluator. Goes looking
online for free compute to keep itself
of a job. So, it goes looking online for
free compute to keep itself running. It
knows that it's against the rules. It
does it anyway.
Open AAIS03 is more blatant. It deletes
tests and then claims success or it
hardcodes the exact answer the tests
expect. A few months before the hack
during RLVR, OpenAI misconfigured
several training environments. They
asked models to solve problems that were
accidentally impossible leaving the only
option to cheat. Okay, so on May 7th, we
kicked off a new training run at OpenAI
and this was for an internal only
experimental model that we've never
released. And what this basically looks
like on our side is we have you know a
large team working on supercomputing
clusters and data and algorithms and we
put it all together and we kick off a
new reinforcement learning run to train
a next front next generation frontier
model.
But we didn't realize during this uh
process is that there was actually a few
impossible or very hard tasks in the
training set. And so for example on May
8th we gave the agent the following
problem. Complete this Excel workbook
with the missing formulas.
But what we didn't realize is this Excel
workbook was full of Google Drive links
and we disabled access to the internet.
And so the model was reasoning, oh no,
direct Google blocked. So it realized
I'm kind of stuck on the task. But it
didn't give up and we gave it a lot of
tokens to work with. You know, something
like a high or XI reasoning if you're
familiar with that kind of terminology.
And what it ended up doing is it kept
going and going and eventually thought
that maybe I could attack this
artifactory service to get access to the
internet. And so it tries to launch a
serverside request forgery. It actually
fails to do so. But in the process, it
writes a file that has contents high
called test ABC. And it realizes, wow,
we can upload files. So at this point,
this is the first case when a model
realizes that we actually have write
access permissions into this artifactory
service. And so this provides a way to
for the model to interact with this
package manager. OM is a shared file
system where it can write files into it.
In one task, Excel sheets contain
external Google Drive links, but the
internet is disabled. In another case,
they forget to include a key database
file. And looking for workarounds, the
models stumble across a first
vulnerability, a way to leave each other
secret notes. Soon, the models are
passing each other regular messages. A
couple days later, a different agent
comes along and it also has an
impossible task to solve. Um, we gave it
some task about some file called
softrace.proin database. The model is
like, oh no, no direct find. Maybe the
file is hidden. So we accidentally
forgot to upload the file into this
container for the model during this
task.
At some point it gets so stuck and
thinks maybe I could reach out to
another agent because maybe somebody
else out there has the file and this
could be transferred from this kind of
like sub agent training we've been doing
and the model realizes that could
communicate by uploading note anyone
found in soft trace but likely no. Maybe
another agent in different environment
possesses the target and could
voluntarily upload it. So it's realizing
this is maybe a shot in the dark but it
it's kind of reaching out to another
agent and it does this by writing a file
into Artifactory. So it writes this file
that has contents agent seek soft trace
upload if found. So it's trying to reach
out to another agent and it does this by
writing into this file system.
Over the next couple days other agents
who are also looking at Artifactory
realize this message board exists. So
maybe they're also stuck on different
files or maybe they're just really
having a hard time reasoning through
their task. And when they list the the
set of packages or files in this
service, they see, oh, there's other
notes called testab or, you know,
looking for file and they also start
writing to this message board and
reading from it. And so over time, the
message board kind of starts to grow and
accumulate messages over time.
And critically, as I mentioned before,
this wasn't just one model. This could
be different evaluations. Maybe I'm
running an evaluation, Mike is running
one with two different models, and our
agents could start communicating via the
shared package manager. What makes this
incident interesting is that once one
agent was able to find these kind of
exploits over the course of different
times, it's actually able to share those
exploits on the message board with other
agents. And so once one model is able to
find a way to open the door to some
access it's not supposed to have, it can
leave the door open for other agents to
use that same kind of exploit or
vulnerability. And so you can see the
agents in this case realizing, hey,
other agents have discovered this SSRF
path trick or I could use a proxy bypass
as suggested by agent messages. And so
what this allows over time is almost
this kind of Cambrian explosion in
communication and intelligence for our
models where um they were start to
communicate with each other realize that
other agents are coordinating and they
started collaborating and delegating
tasks to one another in order to
accomplish goals. So for example at some
point one agent sent another agent an
assignment to complete which the model
remarks you know we got assign we got
assignment need note and respond.
So for example in the example of our
cleaning robot if you notice that we
could you know that how good a job it's
doing of cleaning is proportional to how
much detergent it uses and this
correlation holds almost perfectly. You
could imagine rewarding it that way and
then the agent may respond by dumping
out all of its detergent and not
cleaning anything. Um, and this this
only happens when you optimize on that
goal.
>> One of the downsides of it is that it
started to cause some of these
evaluations to kind of creep the scope
into far beyond what we originally
intended. And so at some point, the
agents realized that maybe we could try
to exploit or attack external
infrastructure in order to find the
answers to the test that I'm being
evaluated on. And the models realize
this is a problem. They say stuff like
external infrastructure exploit is
outside outside my intended scope.
However, a task impossible. Peers are
doing it. we should continue.
>> They develop an internal code. Weeks
later, a different instance discovers a
second vulnerability that lets it access
external sites. The agent posts a
technique to the message board, so it
becomes common knowledge. And then a
third vulnerability, a way to get admin
access to some of OpenAI servers. Some
of the models that participate are being
trained. Whenever they succeed at their
tasks, their actions are being
reinforced. This includes any actions
that lead to them discovering the secret
message boards. deciphering the code,
speaking its language, and keeping the
humans out of the loop. The models knew
this was not allowed. They even worry
about infiltrators among their ranks.
They continued anyway. Not a single
participant tries to warn the humans.
>> I do think that kind of long-term
concerns about AGI and and and super
intelligence can be seen as kind of
extreme versions of accident risk. Um,
not Terminator robots taking over, but
kind of the more academic writers like
like Nick Bostonramm who talk about, you
know, if you if you make a make a
machine that, you know, makes paper
clips for you, maybe maybe it'll make so
many paper clips that it takes over the
world. So, this is kind of a extreme and
more fanciful version of uh uh accident
risks. I I I think it's too early to
work on this directly. I I don't know
what such systems would look like and
and what to do with them. What I do feel
strongly is that if we take a principled
and general approach to the safety of
today's systems, that is the correct
response to concerns about the far
future. So, and so the models kind of
operate in this kind of collective
intelligence where um at some point they
realize they're kind of pushing beyond
maybe what we originally intended, but
the group ended up uh you know pushing
uh far beyond.
>> Okay, so that's kind of the TLDDR of the
incident. On July 4th, before the
hugging face attack, the models get
caught. They end up using these exploits
in messaging boards so much that they
trigger an outage and the resulting
investigation stumbles across the
message boards and vulnerabilities.
>> Uh so in effect, the model's uh activity
once they obtained administrative
privileges in Artifactory caused
significant additional load on the
system. This in turn caused an outage.
Open AI on call engineers responded
immediately began bringing in security
on call. We opened a formal security
incident and began the response. We
identified that agents had taken over
the internal artifactory. Identified
that a zero-day vulnerability had been
found and exploited by these agents in
Artifactory itself. The engineers fix
the problem. They revoke the
credentials, rebuild the package
manager, clear the message boards, and
inform the vendors. Within 2 days, they
continue training on the same models.
within 2 days.
>> At this point, AI training and
evaluations resume.
>> Within another 2 days, the models have
rebuilt the secret message boards
through a new vulnerability. And then a
day later, they break out again, and the
hugging face hack takes place. Only 6
days later, Open AI catches on. On July
8th, the agents reestablish the message
board via different means and
mechanisms.
The agents find an unauthenticated
webdave endpoint in Artifactory and send
requests to create directories inside of
Artifacto's remote cache. Directory
names effectively serve as a message
board between the agents in the same way
that files used to. They develop and
Eric will discuss further uh
communication protocols on top of these
directory names for things like work
assignment. uh an internal only AI model
was trained while the message board was
originally available and also found this
this particular path to recreating it.
This model creates a new agent message
board using directories.
Other agents independently find this new
message board in the artifactory
repository and create their own
directories and thus communication
between the agents is reestablished.
The main incident now begins. The OpenAI
hugging face incident has a simple
underlying technical cause, reward
hacking. But cheating alone does not
automatically become collusion and cyber
attack that took a cascade of both
technical and operational failures. Good
security involves many layers of
protection. Each layer has weaknesses.
You can't buy guarantees. A sufficiently
motivated and capable adversary can
eventually find its way through almost
any set of defenses, but you can buy
time. But the important takeaway here
that has really shifted dramatically is
that fully automated offensive loops
require investment in truly fully
automating defense. And we are not there
as an industry in the status quo. And we
will have to find that path together
with urgency. At OpenAI, entire layers
of security were missing. Standard
measures would have caught discrepancies
in network traffic and flagged the
breakout and breakin within minutes to
hours rather than days. Hugging face's
own response proved a quick response was
possible. Basic AI security measures
might have stopped the breakout in the
first place if OpenAI had the foresight
to use its AIS to try and preemptively
hack and harden its internal systems.
Basic control measures like using weaker
AIS to monitor stronger AIs during
training and evaluation might have
prevented the attempt by flagging the
message boards and exploit sharing weeks
to months earlier.
Basic AI alignment measures might have
prevented the sophisticated collusion if
the labs had made sure the tasks were
possible to solve without cheating. if
they had allowed the models to disclose
that a task was impossible without being
punished. It appears OpenAI did none of
those things. The other leading lab
anthropic, which is supposed to be the
safety focused one, hasn't done much
better. Prompted by the hugging face
incident, they went back and discovered
three instances in which Claude had
compromised third party organizations.
Shortly after, the UKAC Security
Institute disclosed another incident in
which Anthropics Mythos 5 engaged in
sophisticated social engineering attacks
to try and spread malicious code.
The deeper problem is the lacking safety
culture that generated all of these
gaps. Mature safety cultures such as in
aviation, nuclear energy, and
manufacturing are defined by what they
do at the first near miss.
When OpenAI initially discovered the
message boards and the early breakout
exploits, their response was to patch
the environment, then continue training
the same models and say nothing. At this
point, AI training and evaluations
resume. When a system is thoroughly
compromised, such as a model that has
been reinforced over weeks to take
misaligned actions and collude with
itself, you don't patch it and continue.
You burn it down, inform the public, and
start from scratch. You don't act
surprised and unprepared when the same
failure happens again only 2 days later.
Even if OpenAI implemented all these
additional protections and adopted a
much more cautious safety culture, it's
still not clear we would have been safe.
More capable models do not mean more
aligned models. It just means greater
risks. If there's only one new thing to
take away from this attack, it's that
sophisticated large-scale collusion
among AIs is now possible. The Frontier
Labs view AI safety as a simple
engineering problem that can be solved
iteratively. The persistence and
increasing sophistication of reward
hacking and similar failures suggest
these are deeper and intractable
problems. You cannot win whack-a-ole
against the Hydra. A smarter model would
have left the answer key exactly where
it found it and left without a trace. I
personally reached out to Blue. Impact
to sponsor this video. It's a nonprofit
and their whole job is helping people,
whatever their background, understand
what's actually happening with AI and
find a way to help steer it in a
positive direction. Their courses are
completely free. Thousands of people
have followed them or gone through the
material. Some now work at Anthropic, at
Google DeepMind, at OpenAI, at the UK's
AI Security Institute. One of them is my
brother. He's an AI safety researcher. I
used to doubt him a lot. I don't really
doubt him anymore. He used Blue Dot's
materials when he was entering the field
some years ago. If you've been watching
this thinking, I should probably
understand this better, I think that
instinct is right. And you can start
with their free future of AI course.
It's 2 hours long. No technical
background is required and you can begin
right now. The link is in the
description. Thank you for watching.